Yegor: A few words about myself just quickly.
I'm writing software for 25 years,
starting in school.
For about 15 years, I was managing a team,
different teams, up to 120 people, sometimes of developers,
in Ukraine mostly.
I'm also a Java developer myself, a project manager,
and an owner of a company [which]
was, you know, managing all these people.
You can see my Twitter account.
You can see my blog. Please subscribe.
That will be interesting, because everything
I'm gonna say today is explained in my
blog and many different articles. So,
I'm gonna present [to] you the way we manage
programmers, the way we manage projects,
and it's quite different from everything
you've seen in many - in all - other places.
So, that's why you definitely will
be interested to see more content from me.
Here's the subject. Here's the problem.
So, in all my projects, for many, many
years I had the same [issue] as these people are
saying about the industry in general. So
all our projects, all the software
development we have, is basically chaos.
So, we fail, we slip the schedule,
we miss time, we don't complete
the requirements, we don't deliver,
we spend money, and customers are not happy.
I've had that for 15 years - in all - in most
of our projects. And, I found
statistics in the report which says
we're in chaos. And, they say that about
like 94 - which is almost a hundred -
percent of projects actually
fail and have to restart. That's what the
report says about the entire industry.
And, they say that only seven percent of
[the] projects failed because of
technical incompetence. So,
the problem is not with programmers.
The problem is with the management.
They fail because we miss requirements,
because we don't understand what to do,
because we cannot control what we do,
because we cannot manage ourselves. It's not because
we're bad programmers, not because we
don't know Java or Ruby or whatever.
It's because we don't manage ourselves the
right way. And, I've had the same [issue], so
that's why I tried to solve the problem,
and invented the methodology which
actually, in my case, in my experience,
in our projects, actually helped us
a lot to to resolve that [issue] and
be successful. There are five things that -
the methodology is quite big, but
there are five things - I want to
highlight today. They're quite
controversial. That's why it's
interesting. So, five things. How we are
different from everything you've seen before:
Thing number one: Traditionally, we
believe, traditionally you believe, or
they believe, that the teamwork is so
important for the success of the project.
We think that it's so important to
keep the team together, to make sure that
people stay together, that they are
motivated to work together. And, the job
of the manager is to make sure there's a
team there, [and to] make sure that people match
to each other. And, this is
the key factor for the
success of this team, for the success of
the project. So, we just spend a
lot of time on on the team building, on team spirit,
on making sure the people love each other.
And, that's how we guarantee the success.
I think that this approach is for lazy managers.
This is for people
who cannot understand how to
manage programmers. This is for people
who are not really managers. This is what
causes troubles in projects. This is what
this is what leads to loss of the
"A players". Do you know what "A players,
B players, and C players" is? This is the
terminology from the sales [world] actually, but,
I think it can be applied to programming
as well. So, in any team, we have
A players, B players, and C players.
Like senior programmers, medium
programmers, and junior programmers.
So A players, they're always - you know - aiming
for excellence. They're always
trying to do better. C players are
the people who we kind of have to remove
from the team. So, this approach with the
teamwork in our experience is really
good for C players and its really good
for lazy managers. In our case, we do the
opposite. We aim for individual
responsibility. Not team responsibility,
but individual responsibility, always. So,
we don't like the idea of the team in
general. We always pay attention to, "Who
is doing what?", "What's the personal scope
of the task?", and we scope that task
individually. So, we always assign tasks
individually to programmers. We always
give tasks to [the programmers.] We always control the
results of each programmer individually.
So - we never - we don't do the
teamwork at all. So, we clearly define the
rules of the work. And this is
a lot of job we do on the management side.
We always have an architect on our team
who is the person who is
responsible - personally responsible - for
the success of the project,
and who is making all technical decisions.
So, we don't have any democracy
in our teams. We don't vote for technical decisions.
It's always the architects who
makes the decisions and always the team -
the players or developers - who are
responsible for their own scope of work -
for their own tasks. We always work
remotely. So, that's probably what is
different from other teams. But, we work
remotely. So, all our programmers - they
stay in their own places, in their
own countries, and we work. We don't have
a central office at all. So, all our teams
work remotely. And, they communicate
only electronically. So, that also
helps us to stay away from this "team idea"
and to focus on an "individual results" idea.
That's [the] first thing. The second one
is over time. Traditionally - (Yegor points at slides) - What's on
the left it's "traditionally". What's on
the right is our approach. So,
traditionally, programmers are managed by
stress, in most cases. So, we just know
that programmers [are], in general, I mean
managers assume that programmers, in
general, are kind of lazy. So, the best way
to manage them is to put the deadlines
as close as possible, and then stress
them so they work overtime. They work on
the weekend, and that's how they will
achieve better results. That's how they
will be more or less under control.
That's the only way bad managers can
control people - [it] is just to keep them
under stress. And that's how programmers
will do something. So we give them
deadlines, we give them stress, and we get
overtime. So they work more, they spend
more, and we believe, and - managers in
general assume that if people stay
overtime, if they stay in the office,
after the office is closed, these are the
"good programmers". These are the good
developers who stay over time to spend
more time in the office. In our case, it's
quite the opposite. So, we don't want
programmers to work more. We want to work
them less. We expect them to develop and
to commit their code, and to close their
tasks, and to close their tickets, and to
do anything voluntarily - only when they
want to do that. So, we allow our
programmers to reject tasks if they
don't want to do them. If they don't feel
like it. So, we just give them tasks and
allow them to choose whether it's a good
time for them to work on them or not.
Whether it's a good task for them or not. And,
whether it's a good time for them to do
it now. And, in most cases, most projects,
our programmers, when the project is full
of work - and, we have a lot of tasks - they
spend three, four hours a day for the
development, not more. So, we never work
eight hours a day. Forget the
overtime. We don't have overtime at all.
So three, four hours a day. It's - in my
experience - it's the maximum time a good
programmer can spend a day for actually
productive work. And they do it
voluntarily because, I'll say about it
later but, because we pay for results,
that's why they're really interested to
do the work, because, they get - you know -
they get money for that. So, they do
it when they feel like it. Sometimes they
commit a lot of time one week and the
next week they commit less time. So, the
graph jumps up and down. And, it's not
under control of the manager. The manager
doesn't push the person - any developer - to
any amount of work. If we don't
have enough - you know - resources, if we
don't have enough people to close all
our tasks, then our managers have to find
more people. Then we have to find more
resources - I mean developers, programmers,
resources, whatever. So, we find more of
these resources, and it's a job of a
manager how to - you know - to find more
more resources and give that
tasks to that people. But, we never stress
programmers. We never expect them to work
more than they want to. So, it's the job
of a manager. That's what I'm saying. So,
our managers are way more busy than
traditional managers, because they really
have to do the management work. They
don't need to stress anybody. They need
to schedule tasks on a timeline. So, we
don't have ever overtimes at all. Number
three is "Learnings." I'm going from this
from the [least] critical to the
more and more critical. So, "Learning".
Traditionally, in any project which I've
seen before, people, programmers, the core,
are the main holder of information and
knowledge. So, this is the most
knowledgeable part of any project. This
is the most important part of any
project. If programmers know enough about
the stuff they develop, then the project
is more or less successful. The more they
know, the more knowledgeable they are, the
higher the chances of success. And, if
somebody - someone new - [a]
new programmer joins the project, then it
takes some time to ramp up that person,
to - you know - to teach that person all
the new technologies and everything
which is in the project. And, it takes a
month. It takes two months. And, it takes
sometimes three months. So, it takes long
enough to bring somebody new to the
project. This is the traditional way. That's
what we have in most projects. And, in
most cases, we have so-called experts -
subject-matter experts - so, people who
know most of the - they possess the
majority of the knowledge in the project.
So, they know a lot. And, these people are
the key decision-makers in the project.
If we lose that person in a traditional
environment, if we lose that expert, we
lose a lot. And that's why [these] people
kind of start to control the owners of
the project. It's not that the manager
who controls the the development
environment. It's the people, the experts,
who control people with the money. So,
they tell the customers what's going to
happen, not the customer says what's
gonna happen, but the people who are
experts. They start to manipulate people
with money. This is what I've
seen in a lot of places. We change that
completely. In our case, we don't really
like the idea of having people who know
too much in the project. We want
our artifacts - our documents - to know
"too much". We want our product to be self-
explainable so that anybody tomorrow
joins the project and can
understand everything in just a few
hours. It may sound crazy, but it really
happens in our projects. We bring
sometimes new programmers to the project
which is one year old. And, that new
developer starts writing code and making
new classes, writing new unit tests,
committing code, in just one hour. So, it
doesn't take a month or two months to
learn because we don't have experts. We
don't have people who know "too much". We
only have documents, and source code, and
diagrams which explain everything. How we
achieve that: We - first of all - we rotate
people. We change people from project to
project. We move them because we
understand that the more experts we have
the bigger is the trouble
for us. We don't want experts. We want
people [to] be - How [do] they say it? - like commodity
programmers. So, they're like - they can
work here, and then, tomorrow they can
work there. So they can go from project
to project and can contribute there as
effectively as they were contributing
yesterday in a different project. So,
first of all, we did - i'll say a
few words about it later - But, here we
rotate them. We change them. And, second,
we promote the idea of "always blame the
project, don't blame yourselves". If you
start working in a project, you don't
understand anything. You don't need to
learn. You need to say that the project
is not is not sufficient enough for me
to understand how it works. If you open
the piece of code, if you look at it, you
don't understand how it works.
You don't learn it. You don't ask anybody.
You don't find an expert. You just say,
"Hey, your class or your piece of code is
not clear enough. So, fix it." And then, we
fix it for you. And then, it will be easier
for you to understand it later. So, we
always ask programmers to blame us - the
project - for not being clear enough. And,
we fix that. We improve the quality of
the documentation. And, we bring it back
to you and ask, "Can you fix it now?" If you
can't fix it now, then again you blame
us. And then, in a number of [those] cycles,
eventually the project becomes as clear
for you so you can understand it in half
an hour. You probably have questions.
We'll get back to it. [audience laughs] Number four: We have
five in total. Number four: "Meetings"
Traditionally, people believe that the
more programmers communicate, the more
meetings they have, the higher the
chances of success in the project. The
more - the closer - they stay together, the
more of these face-to-face communications
they have, the higher the chances that
they will actually understand what's
going on. And, they will produce something.
So, that's why we have these Slack chats. We
have these Skype calls. We have
conference calls. Sometimes, the senior
developers spend half of their day
or maybe sometimes the full day in just
meetings and just talking and talking
and exchanging information. And, this is
what - you know - managers believe is a good
way to do. They think that senior
developers have to be in [those] meetings.
They [the senior developers]
have to spend time on talking instead of
writing code. And, even [the] Agile manifesto
says so, like [that] face-to-face communications
is always better than documentation. We
completely disagree with that.
We believe that the more meetings you
have, the more informal communications,
the more these chats you have, and the
more face-to-face calls or whatever you
call it by - "remote calls" - doesn't matter.
The more you have of that, the bigger the
trouble you [have] caused to the project.
Because, you exchange the information
which stays nowhere. We talk to each
other. I explain [to] you how it works. You
understand how it works. But tomorrow,
somebody else will join the project. And,
that person will not know how it works.
So, we will have to explain again. We'll
have to explain again. So, every minute
spent in the meeting is the wasted money
of the customer. So, the more we talk, the
more we exchange information informally,
the more money we waste, which the
customer is paying us. So, good developers,
I believe, and - we seriously preach
this idea - the good developers - good
engineers - they exchange informations
through documents, through
diagrams, through the source code, through
formal written communication. [Good engineers use written communication] which is
maintainable, which we can get back to in
a year, in a month, in a week, in an hour,
and understand why that decision was
made, who made that decision, [and] what was the
reason behind that decision. To achieve
that - you know - not to enforce,
but encourage people to actually use
documents instead of calls, we don't
allow them to call. [laughs] We just - that's so
easy. [clapping in the audience]
We just - we just don't. [laughs] They just don't
have phone numbers of each other. So, we
don't have that Slack chats. We don't
have that Skype calls. They don't know, I
mean, they know each other, but only
through... We work on GitHub. So, they only
know their GitHub accounts. All they
can do in a project... If I don't know
anything, for example: I joined the
project. There are like 20 developers
in there. I don't have some
information. I can't call anybody. I can't
ask anybody. All I can do is I can submit
the ticket and say, "Hey, this piece of
information is missing from that
document. Can you please - you know - fix
that and put that piece of information
into that document?" And, somebody will fix
that for me. I don't care who it's gonna
be. I don't care who's gonna fix that. All
I care about is that I look at the
document and I find that missing piece
of information. That's the idea. So, if you
allow programmers - you know - to talk to
each other, they will. If you allow them
to call, they will, because it's naturally
better for us - you know - to communicate -
you know - face to face. Just - here's the - my
friend sitting next to me. I'm gonna ask
him. I'm not gonna - you know -
get the document. I'm gonna just ask and
get the information.
We completely disallow that. For us, it's
easy because we work remotely. So, all our
developers are somewhere. They're like -
you know - in different countries, in
different time zones. So, we don't have a
central place. So, we just keep them like
that. And, we don't allow them to - you know -
to get into some Slack chat and talk. All
they can do is communicate through
ticketing systems, through the source
code. And that's how we achieve that
results. So, we have only documents and
only diagrams. And, I'm saying it again.
Sometimes, it's very often we have
projects which are one year old and the
new developer jumps in and there's like
50 thousand lines of code of Java code -
like serious Java code. And, the new
developer jumps in and starts writing
code in just one hour.
It's unachievable in a
traditional project configuration. The
last one. And [then] we [will] have questions. "Salaries":
The biggest problem. So,
traditionally, we believe
that - I mean, everybody believes that - it's
so important to keep the developer happy
and to keep the developer safe. And, it's -
you know - to get and keep the loyalty from
the person. So, we need long time, long
term contracts, good salary, paid every
month, and that's how we're gonna
achieve - you know - good results from that
particular person. So, we usually pay for
when - not we, but you - you usually get paid for
per month, per time, sometimes per hour,
sometimes per month. But, it's always for
time. You just sit in front of the
computer, and you do something, and they
pay you for this time. You achieve the
result, they pay you. You don't achieve
the result, they still pay. You work,
they pay you.
You don't work, they still pay you. That's
a huge problem, I believe, especially for
A players. Remember that A, B, C players. We
have "A players", people who really want to
achieve something, and we have "C players"
who just enjoy being in front of the
computer. So, the A players,
they don't like that. They will
leave your project. And, they will not be
productive at all because this
format - you know - puts everybody on the
same level. [That is] because, if I'm the A player
and I produce results, I'm still
paid more or less at the same level as
the C player who produces zero results.
And then another [issue] is "soft skills". So then, in
the end, to make a decision [about] who's gonna
get more salary, who's gonna get the raise,
who's gonna get the - you know - who's gonna
get fired - we use "soft skills". Who is the
nicer guy in the team, who talks more,
who is more communicative, who is the
good match for the team - that's how we
decide who gets the raise. [This is] instead of
looking at the real results. Instead of
looking at the numbers. I don't know [if it's]
numbers but, [I mean] the actual results that
people provide. So, we use the "soft skills".
It completely demotivates A
players, in my experience. So, we remove
that. We don't have salaries at all. Well,
we pay money, but we don't pay salaries. [laughs]
We pay for results. Every time
developers complete something - close the
ticket, file a bug. Basically two things:
Close the ticket, and file the bug. So, fix
the bug or file a bug. We pay for that.
And, we do micro payments. So, we pay our
developers in like really small,
micro payments. We can do that because we
work with remote programmers and
freelancers mostly. And, we pay them
through like PayPal, BitCoin,
whatever. So, we just - you know - we have
these transactions - many transactions -
every day. And, the more they commit, the
more they, not commit but, the more
results they produce... It's not about the
number of lines of code,
It's not about some productivity metrics.
It's about, close the task, or not close
the task. Here's the problem: You either
solve the problem or you don't solve the
problem. When the problem is solved... And,
we have small problems. We always have
small tasks, half an hour, or one hour,
really micro tasks... The task is closed. We
pay. The task is not closed - we don't pay.
So, there's no salaries. This is how we
make it so easy to measure the
performance, and productivity, and
motivation of everybody in the project.
Because, we - I mean - we don't pay in the
end of the month. We pay when the project -
when the task - is closed.
So, I'm basically done. I think you will
have questions but let me [first] summarize. So,
in this model of work which I just
explained, we've been working for about
three years already. 250 developers went
through this model. So, 250 people
actually tried that and got some money
from us in different tasks
and different projects. [These projects are] mostly Java, 90%
is Java. 25 projects completed. Commercial
and open source. We have open source
projects as well, so you can look at them.
Come to me later, [and] I'll give you my
coordinates. You can look at the GitHub
account. And, you will see a number of
projects which were completed using this
technology - this approach. And, you
will see how we communicate to each
other in GitHub tickets. So, you will see
how we get rid of these meetings [completely].
And, all our communications are there. You
will see even how we pay programmers
because all these like payment - you know -
successful payment notifications are
there in GitHub. It will be quite
interesting. And, we produced about
300,000 lines of Java code. It's pretty
big amount of code. And, all of these
projects were really successful
comparing to what I had before for many
years. So, I'm asking you to follow me.
Subscribe to the blog and you will
learn more. So, now questions from you
guys.  [audience applause]
Moderator: So, we have a plenty of questions in
slider and I will start with the most
voted ones. Okay? And, so you talk about
information but, what about designing
together? Because the design is - it's - a
product of a conversation.
Yegor: Well, yeah. It's... yeah. I've heard the
question many times. So, people again
believe that the design is the
result of the conversation of the
work of the group. But, in my experience
it's not that true. In my experience, the
design is always the result of one
person thinking and asking people around.
So, when we start a project, we always
have some person as an architect - in
the role of the architect - and that
person is responsible for creating the
skeleton, the prototype of the product.
That person may collect information from
other people, asking, "What do you think
about this? I'm not sure about choosing
the database. So, tell me which database
would you think I should use? Tell me
about the technology I should use." So,
questions are welcome. That the architect
has to have - has to ask - questions, this
is perfect. But, the final decision -
the final design - has to be made by one
person. That's what I believe.
Moderator: Buf if they get paid for answers, if they don't get paid, they don't get to ask questions.
Yegor: We pay for answering questions, of course. But,
all questions are like tickets. So, let's
say, for example, you're a good database
engineer, yeah. And, I am like an architect.
And, I don't really know what kind of
database to choose, MySQL or
PostgreSQL. So, I'm sorry, I'm submitting a
ticket and saying, "Hey, I['m] miss[ing] a
comparison of MySQL and PostgreSQL. I
need a comparison provided for me. This
is a task for you for an hour. So, you
work for an hour, give me the table, a
spreadsheet, comparing why MySQL is
better for us and why PostgreSQL is better
for us. And, I say, "Thank you very much." I
know that. Now, let me make a decision. So,
that's how it should be - iteratively
goes through questions, and answers, and
then finally, I will be able to make my
decision. Again, it's not easy. It's way
easier to sit together in the same room
and say, "Hey, what do you think about
PostgreSQL?" and you say, "Well, MySQL
is better." "Oh, that's right, thank you very
much!" and then I make a decision. But then,
in two months, somebody will come and
say, "Hey, why the decision for MySQL
was made?" and, I'm gone from the project
because - you know - they fired me already.
You're gone as well. [audience laughs] They fired
you, too. And then, the question is, "Who
made the decision?" Well, there were two
guys - you know - yeah. I still have the
phone number of the one guy. Let me call
him. But instead, we're gonna have the
detailed conversation. And, the ticket for
that. And, everybody will be able to jump
in and see, "Yeah, that guy who is
fired asked the question, "Why MySQL?"
And, another guy submitted the detailed
explanation of them. That's a perfect meeting traceability.
Moderator: My friends, there
are so many questions in slider. Go
ahead and vote for questions, because,
oh, let's make it moderated, OK? I'll
ask the top most questions. And, there are
many. So, there is the - it's not a
question. It's like a complaint: Three
hours of work, are you kidding? My manager
will kill me. The stock will decrease. And,
the company will close. Yegor: For three hours
of work? Moderator: Three hours of work, are you kidding me? Yegor: Yeah
per day. Yeah. I believe honestly that a
productive - like a good engineer - Well, I'm
talking about myself, first of all. So, I
can't imagine working for eight hours a
day on something which is not my
personal project - you know - which I really
love. So, working for somebody, for some
project, for money, 3-4 hours a day, is the
total maximum and normal - you know - good
engineer can really handle, I think.
So,
otherwise, it's eight hours and three
five hours of Facebook watching - you know -
out of this.
So, it's gonna be three hours, in any case.
So, you're not going to be productive for
eight hours, it's not possible. You can
really write code for three [hours]. Sometimes,
even two hours is enough. But, I think
that, in general, programmers have to be
paid way better. So, we need to earn way
more. We need to make more money per hour
and spend less time in front of the
computer. You know [what I mean]? So, I don't know how
much you're making, but an average like
say, for example, now programmers are
making like - personaly, I dunno - 25 euros an
hour, thirty euros an hour.
They have to make a hundred [Euros], but work
three times less. In this case - but - they
work three times less. But - they have to be
paid for results, not for the time. So now,
we are all paid for eight hours - you know -
from the morning till the evening.
Whatever I do, you pay me. But, it should
be the other way. It should be the
opposite: You pay me way more, but only
for the results I produce. In the end, it
will be the same amount of
money in cash. Maybe a little bit more,
but I will be focused on results.
I'll be really motivated and
interested to actually work, instead of
just pretending I'm working, just sitting
there. And, just going to, okay, so the
three hours is that. Three hours is the
maximum. Well, four. Moderator: The next question: Who
decides how much time the problem
takes to solve? If it's the
business, how can [they] estimate? They always
think the task is easy.
Yegor: Well, yeah. We just, in our
approach, we always give the same
budget for all tasks. So, we always give
it a really small budget. And then, we use
this technology where we allow
developers to return back the code in
incomplete state. So, I guess you're
developers, right? Who are the developers?
Who actually writes code here? Like 75%,
maybe more. So, you should understand that.
Let's say you get a task [where] you have to
implement that feature. And, the feature
is way bigger than one hour. So, we don't
ask you to - you know - to... We ask you to
cheat, basically. We ask you to implement
the - provide the high level
implementation with certain parts not
implemented yet. So, we say, this feature,
for example, I have to be able to click
the button and log in. And, this is one
hour for you. And, you understand that's
one hour. It's not enough. It should be
like five hours. So, you just create a
button. It says "log in". It's clickable.
But, it doesn't log in. So, you just return
back the code to me - to the master
branch - and say, the button is there but,
there is a marker [which] says "to-do later:
Implement the log-in this and that way."
So, you kind of help us to improve - to
design that. And, by introducing the
high level solution, and then keeping the
markers of where other programmers have
to contribute more. So, you return back
the code with the markers. And then, these
markers we convert back to new tasks. So,
we ask developers to help us break down
the problem into smaller pieces. That's
how we do it. Moderator: Next question. Yegor: We call it
"puzzle driven development". So, we call
these pieces "puzzles". So, we give you
the task. You return it back with puzzles
inside. And then, somebody else will solve
[those] puzzles. And while people
solve the puzzles, they will introduce
new puzzles. So, when we start developing,
it's just a few puzzles. And then, it goes
like that. [Yegor gestures an expanding mountain with his hands] So, there are like
hundreds of puzzles. And then, when all of
them get fixed, the software gets back [together],
and it starts to work well. It becomes
completely functional. If you're interested,
come back to me later. I'll explain.
Moderator: Next question.
Isn't there a lack of quality? Developers
deliver the code and go. There is no
motivation in delivering good code. Who
decides whether to pay or not?
Yegor: Yeah, that's a good question. So, definitely. And,
we really ask our developers
to be lazy. So, be lazy. Don't try to do
more than you can do. But, be prepared
that the quality control is really
strict in front of you. So, when you get
the task and you have to implement
something, do as little as you can. You
don't need to - you know - to make it hard.
You don't make the quality higher than
the quality bar we have in front of you.
And, the quality bar is quite high. So, for
you to return back the code to us, to the
master branch, it has to pass two code
reviews plus the automated merge
instruments. So, we're going to merge your
branch back to master branch only if all
the tests and all the static analysis
and all the coverage control, everything
passes. So, for example, they'll give you
the example of how high is the quality
bar for us. Static analysis is the step
in the build for us. So, we
don't with - The build is not going to
pass
if the static analyzer says there are
any bugs, any warnings, [or] any complaints. You
know what static analysis is, right? Do
you know what static analysis is? Okay,
good.
So you understand the static analysis is
usually is used as a tool which is - you
know - which we run on the code and which
generates some - you know - spreadsheets,
some interesting web pages, which we'll
look at and say, "Hey, the rate of our
static analysis warnings is a bit lower
than the yesterday. That's great, but,
there's still a lot of them - Still a lot
of complaints." Look at your project. Run
the static analyzer for your project. No
matter what language you're using, you
will see there many of them. In our case,
there is zero. So, we run the static
analysis on the entire code base. And,
there should be zero warnings, which is
really difficult to achieve. If you're
serious, if your static analysis is
configured properly, it's really
difficult to achieve. Especially, there
are many people working there. And, the
code base is quite big in our case. No
matter how big is the code base, no
matter how
many developers are there, we're
not gonna merge your stuff unless
there's no bugs. There's no static
analysis complaints. So, that's an
example of how high is the quality bar.
So, what I'm saying is that, we're kind of
building a conflict. Here's your task.
You're gonna get the money when it's
merged. But, you're not gonna get [your code] merged
if the quality is not high enough. And, we
do it for every single task. So, for each -
for every single increment. For every
single developer who is trying to change
the code and commit the new stuff into
our code base into master. We always
check the quality. We'll always check the
quality. So, when the project is one year
old, we merged already a thousand pull
requests. And, for all these thousand pull
requests, for thousand[s of] steps, micro
increments, we check the quality again,
again, and again. So, in the end, the
quality is really high. Again, you can
check our GitHub projects in Java. You
will see how high is
the quality of our code. Moderator: Okay, great.
There was a comment. Maybe you have
something to say about it. Even prisoners
are allowed one call. Yegor: [laughs] Well, yeah. For the
call. Yeah. I've heard that complain a lot.
So, people saying like, "Hey, we're people.
We love to call each other. We love
to say good morning sometimes. What kind
of work is that when there is like, yeah,
people don't talk to each other?" I also
thought so. I had that fear years ago
when I introduced that [no call policy]. I was like hey,
programmers not gonna like it, because
they're kind of used to talking to each other.
They love these, all these Slack chats, and
hashtags, and everything. But, when we're
talking about A players, when we're
talking about senior developers, they
really don't like that. They like to stay
focused on their stuff, which is really
interesting for them. They have other
places where we can - where they can - talk
to somebody. They can - you know - have beer.
They can smile. They can joke. That the
work and the project is the place where
people are interested in professional
growth, not - you know - interpersonal
communications, in my experience. Because,
let's face the reality: The project is
just a temporary group of
people who have nothing in common
basically. In most cases, they're
from different countries, they're from
different cultures, they're from
different - they're different ages, they're
just different people. They come together
because they are Java experts, for
example. And, this is what they have in common.
That's it. They're not friends. They never
been to school together. They don't live
together. They don't have - you know - their
families are not friends. So,
they want to focus on stuff which they
have in common. And, when traditional
projects - you know - trying to make a team
of them, trying to use these
team-building things, and trying to - you
know - say like, "Hey, we're one family",
They're not one family. They don't have
anything in common. Like - you know - I'm
40. He's 16. What kind of family is this?
And, this is really annoying for A
players. This is really annoying for
senior developers to be in the team like
that when people are trying to put them
together and say it's one family, one
team, "we're all together". They['re] just [like,] "Leave
me alone.
Let me code. Let me - [you] know - write the code.
Let me focus on that [which] we are doing."
Exactly that. We're just saying remove
that interpersonal - you know - stop and
focus on this, on the technical, on the
technical problems, and people really
appreciate it - A players. C players, yeah,
they complain. They complain they say
like, "Hey, where's your Slack chat? How can
I call you? I can explain. You let me call
you and I explain everything." We're just
saying, "No, here's the ticket. Submit the
ticket. You don't like the objective code?
You don't like the documentation? Submit
the ticket." And he's like, "Yeah, it's not
really how I'm used to them to do that.
Let me call, it'd be easier for me. It's a
clear indication that he's a C player.
Or she. Moderator: This is always a man. So, let's
move on. If people are only paid for
results, how do you handle periods where
people have less productivity? They have
personal issues, for example. But, they are
temporary. Yegor: It's their own problems. I mean,
yeah. But, we, there... We're adults, I mean.
It's business. So, we, this is... We pay
people. I mean, our rates are high.
That's first. So, we pay people. We work
remotely. And, there are people from
mostly from not really expensive
countries. And, we pay like 40 bucks an
hour, 45 dollars an hour. It's pretty high
rate. So, we allow them to make money
while they are productive,
while they have time. So, they are - you
know - they should be smart enough. They
should be grown-up people to manage
their own finance, to manage their own
money. So, save something for the time
which for your vacation or whatever. So,
we're not trying to - you know - we're
trying to respect our
people with - our programmers - we're trying
to treat them as - you know - as equal.
They're not kids. They're not
children. So, they don't need to be
patronized like in traditional teams.
Like, yeah, we're gonna cover your
vacation, just sit in the office. It, again,
it doesn't motivate A players. It
motivates C players. With those, like, hey,
I'm productive now because it's luck.
Maybe tomorrow I will stop being
productive because, who knows. What's
gonna happen? They're afraid of that. And,
that's why they want to be patronized,
protected. They want somebody to take
care of them. We just let them take
care of themselves. So, we treat them
equally. This is the project. We have
money here. You produce something. You
give the results. We transfer the money
from here to here. And then, we're - you
know - just go our own ways. So, we don't
have any vacations, paid vacations,
anything. Moderator: Who is responsible for the
final production result? Yegor: Well, for the
final productions result, is the
architect. So, technically, we have an
architect, like I said, in any project. And,
that person is responsible for final
production result and responsible. We
don't like the word responsible, because,
responsibility means some - you know - means
that you're gonna lose something if
something happens. In our case, it doesn't
happen. So, in our case, if the project
doesn't work in the end, then, you know,
that's it. So, there is no - you know -
financial responsibility of that person.
We're not gonna say like, "Hey, now you're
gonna pay us something because you were
the architect for a month and you didn't
produce anything." So, the word "responsible",
in this case, we don't like to use, even
with the customer. So, when customers come
to us and say like, "Hey, are you gonna be
responsible? Is [it] gonna work?" We say, "No, we
can't guarantee that the software will
work. All we can guarantee [is] that the way
we manage the development is effective."
It's like it's, I'm always giving this
example with the taxi driver. You go into
the taxi and you ask, "Can you guarantee
that you will take me to the airport?" If
the taxi driver is professional enough,
he will say like, "No, I can't guarantee
you that, because, anything may happen. The
car may break. There's gonna be a
roadblock, whatever. Anything can happen.
All I can guarantee you [is] that I have a
GPS, I have a map, I have a driving
license, I have the gas in my car.
Let's go. Let's go and see what happens.
So, we are together in this
journey, you know? The same should happen
in software development. Any attempt to
put responsibility on
on the team like say, "Hey guys. Whatever
happens, you have to
make it work. It's just against the idea
of software development. It's wrong. You
shouldn't. Well, if you [are] a
customer, you shouldn't do it like that.
You should check how your
team works. How effective are the
mechanisms and methods they use to
organize their work? And then, see what
happens.
And also, it's also related to the
estimate. So, sometimes people say like
"Can you estimate the project? How much
will it cost?" We can't estimate, but, we
never put that in the contract [that] we can't
give you some number and say like, "We
estimate it's gonna cost a hundred
thousand dollars." Yes, that's an estimate.
But, it may be a million easy. So, we just
gonna see what happens. We will
drive. We're in the taxi. We will drive.
But, if on that way straight there, if
there will be some - you know - detours and
some roadblocks, then we will make
detours. And, it will cost you more and
more and more. The only thing we can
guarantee is that we're not gonna cheat.
We're not gonna - you know - make extra
detours. That's what you can blame
us for. But, don't blame us for - you know -
for the road being longer than you were
expecting. That's the philosophy. I mean,
not every customer will like that, but...
Moderator: Okay, let's move on. How do you know that
your developers didn't form up hidden
secret chat groups? [Yegor and audience laugh] How do you know that
your developers does not form up a
secret chat groups? Yegor: Well, yeah. We thought
about that. And - you know - when they start
working, they - sometimes they try.
Sometimes they try. [audience laughs] I had - it's a real
story. I had a story with the customer. So,
the customer came to us. And, I explained
the idea, like how we work, and he
said like, "I love it. Let's do it your way."
And, then we started to work. And then, in
about a month, I realized that I
don't have enough - you know - tickets. So,
he's coming to me and giving me some
information which I can't find hidden in
tickets. So, he's saying like, "Hey, we're
using that technology. It's really great."
and I'm like, "Yeah, but, who made that
decision?" and he's like, "Yeah, that
developer made the decision." and I'm
like, "Where? Where's the ticket?" and he's
like, "Forget it. No problem. You already
made it." And then, I realized that he
created the chat - the customer. And, [he]
invited developers there. And, they
started to talk there. And, I'm like - and
me and my managers were like - watching in
the tickets. And, the tickets - the amount of
tickets - go down.
The conversations stop there. But, the
information - but the code - is being
written. So, they write code. They make
decisions. But, we don't see what's going
on. And then, I talk to the customer and
said like, "Do you have some - you know - do
they talk to them?" And he's like, "Yeah.
What's wrong with that?" And I'm like, "Dude.
I told you; that's completely against our -
you know - our principles, our
philosophy." And he's like, "All right. All
right. I promise you. No more talking." And
then, again, the same. So, he just
opened the box. And, he ruined the whole
thing. So, in the end, the project failed.
In the end, it was nowhere, because we
completely lost control of the situation.
You know - you understand why, because
these people started it all. They started
to make decisions. And then, this -
we completely lost control. That's it. So,
the project failed, and quite -
Yeah. They told him like - this customer - I
told him like, "Look, I can't be
responsible anymore for anything because
you['re] just doing things which
are completely wrong. You shouldn't do
that. You shouldn't allow them to have
that conversation." So, it happened. And,
second question. Yes. Moderator: So, one more
question. What stops me from generating
the bugs [that] I will fix for your money?
What stops me from generating
the bugs that will get fixed for your
money? So, basically -
Yegor: Okay, yeah. That's a good question. So, what
stops the developer from generating -
while writing - the code and introducing
some bugs which will be fixed
later. And then, the developer will make
more money, right? That's the question.
Well, first of all we assign. But, we
assign bugs to fix not to the same
people who introduced them. So, we
randomly assign tickets. So, let's say
you're the developer. So, you create a
piece of code. And, in that piece of code
there is some bugs intentionally made.
Okay, you made them intentionally. But,
then these bugs will be fixed by that
person, that person, and that person - randomly.
So, there is no real reason for the
developer to introduce bugs. Like, there's
no, I haven't seen that any, like never. So -
Say again? [listens to audience member speaking inaudibly, then audience laughs] Well, unless they have a secret
chat. But, *we* assign tickets. So, they
don't make this decision. We always give
them tickets. We say like, "Hey, Jeff. This
is your ticket." You can't choose it. I
mean, you can say, "No, give me that
one." It's always randomly only always
to random people. That's how we actually
solve the problem with no experts at all.
So, because every time we give
bugs and troubles to differ
people. So, they always have to
understand the new piece of code. So,
there [is] always something in the code
base - something new arrived into the
person, and it helps. So, I haven't
seen that. Moderator: Okay, great.
Another question: So, how do you decide
how much do you pay for a particular
task? Yegor: Well, like I said, we always give the
same. We say in the same budget. Let's say
one hour, and one hour means multiplied
by the hourly rate of the developer. So,
we have like a group of developers. Let's
say 20 people in the project. And, that
person is 50 bucks an hour, or that
person is 30 bucks an hour. So, and then,
we have a bug for one hour. So, we
randomly select the person and give it
to that person. Okay, it's gonna cost $50.
[audience member speaking inaudibly]
Yeah, like, I just explained before. So, we just
always say one hour. We don't know - we
don't estimate. We don't care. So, we just
say one hour. Well, in our case, it's half
an hour. We try it - one hour - but, now we
use 30 minutes. So, it's always half an
hour. And, we allow developers to cheat and
return back the code - return back to fix
not completely fixed. So, sometimes we
have bugs which takes an oh, five, seven,
ten steps. So, let's say, I create - there's
a bug. I assign it to you. You fix it not
completely. You just say, "Hey, I just - for
example - I introduced the unit test which
which proves that this is not the
problem."
But, I don't know what the problem is. So,
I introduce new unit test. And, I put a
new marker saying like, "Hey, please
investigate further, because it looks
like - here's the new unit test but - it
doesn't prove that the bug is there." I've
returned that code back. The new
developer picks up the marker and tries
again. Again, it can [be] that the developer
can't do anything. Again, the new code comes
into master branch. The new developer is
assigned. A new developer is assigned. So,
we can jump back and forth, back and
forth, on these iterations, sometimes for
ten times, and eventually that will be
fixed. So, the total cost of the bug will
be 10 multiplied by 30 minutes. There's
gonna be 300 minutes - the total budget.
But, it's going to be 10 increments. 10
Increments with 10 people, which is a way
more manageable situation
comparing to one person [spending] 300
minutes. "Hey, here's your task work for
300 minutes" which means, what, five hours.
Maybe,
you will fix it. In our case, it's going to be
ten people touching that problem. Ten
people. Eventually, the person number ten
will fix it.
Which one is manageable - more manageable?
Obviously, the - our approach. So, we don't
estimate. We just always say thirty
minutes, half an hour, whatever. You do
half an hour, do something, do something,
do something. And then, we iterate, iterate,
iterate. Moderator: Okay, great. And what about "Ops"
now what about operations and
infrastructure? How do you pay for that?
Yegor: Well for DevOps, it's kind of something
we haven't touched like seriously. So, I'm
not sure how it's gonna work for DevOps.
For the current situation with DevOps
where people actually - you know - configure
servers and install something on servers.
So, my answer is, "I don't know."
We'll try. We haven't touched that area
yet. Maybe with the immutable servers -
which i think is gonna be the future -
when we'll have mutable servers, and then
the entire infrastructure will be kept
in the in the repository as a code, and
everything will happen in the code, and
then the infrastructure will be
automatically deployed to production
like in one-click, then probably the
DevOps will be equal to developer. And
then, the problem will be solved. But,
right now it's more like people with the
SSH consoles. So, it's difficult to do.
Moderator: If the server is down, the spacer duty also
just open a ticket? Yegor: Well, in most cases. Yeah, in
most cases of the server is down, we also
open the ticket. We also open the ticket
and say, "Hey, somebody fixd that." And,
sometimes - it's a good question -
sometimes, we need that ticket to be
fixed now instead of in five hours. And,
[in] that case, we increase the budget. We just
say, "It's not 30 minutes. It's two hours."
Even though we understand it's a work
for five minutes or 15 minutes. We
just multiply - we boost - the budget. We say
like "multiple"
and it means like the developer will
pick it up immediately and will try to
do everything to close because the
budget is way higher. So, we can - we
actually motivate by money which is [a]
really good thing.
So, most people say that money is not a
motivator. We completely disagree with
that. Money is the greatest motivator.
That is the greatest motivator ever
invented in human history. We don't
need anything else. We don't need [these] -
you know - tennis tables in the office. We
don't need these coffee machines. We need
money. Just give money to people in a
clear way so the developers will
understand why the money coming there,
how to increase the amount of money. I
don't need this soft skills. I don't - I
don't need to please my manager. I just
need to close more tickets. This is, I
think, the way more productive - you know -
approach to motivating people. There's
the question here. Maybe, yeah. [audience member speaks inaudibly] Taxes? Well,
we pay taxes. Programmers pay taxes. So,
programmers want to send money to -
programmers, they pay all their own
taxes, of course. Yeah. Moderator: How much do you pay
managers and how well for managers? Yegor: We
pay in the same, well, we also pay by task.
And so, the more tasks a manager is
managing, is assigning, closing, assigning,
closing, the more money the manager gets.
So, we're always trying to attach
everybody in the project for results. So,
the more the project produces - the more
we deliver to the customer more code - the
more everybody - you know - gets. And, the
customers appreciate it. And, we build
them like that. So, in
the end of the week, end of
the month, we just show the customer the
total amount of tasks we closed, bugs we
solved, and this is the amount of money the
customer pays. Yeah. Moderator: Okay. Who is breaking
up work in chunks? What if the chunk is
too big? Yegor: Well, I just explained that. I
explained that. We just - you know - we just
give the full chunk to [the] developer and
then we allow [the] developer to cheat. So,
that's how we break it. Moderator: Do you even have
permanent employees in the company,
except yourself? Yegor: Well, we - I'm, in general,
against permanent employment. I think
it's a modern form of
slavery.
So, this long-term employment is,
well, it's really good for lazy
developers. It's really, it's
perfect. Because, like I said, no matter
what you do, you get the money. But, it's
not really good for people who are - you
know - who are
self-motivated, who are interested to
grow, who wants to get pleasure from the
work. So, this full time employment -
long-term employment - is really not
productive. It's everywhere right now. All
companies pay that. And - you know - it's
really difficult to fight against that.
But, I think the future is different. I
think, in the future, we'll get more money
per hour, but, we'll get
paid for results. I think that's the
future for professional development - not
what we have right now. What we have
right now is, like I'm saying, it's modern
slavery of the 21st century. It's gonna
go. Moderator: Okay, and the last question. From
me actually to the audience. Yegor: Yeah. Moderator: How many
people agree with this approach? Yegor: See? 50%.
Moderator: Thank you, Yegor. That was awesome. Yegor: Thank
you very much.
[Applause]